running, jumping and dancing. I love to dance. However, in my mid-twenties, I began to experience a series of inexplicable falls. And a few years later, I was diagnosed with a recessive genetic condition called hereditary inclusion body myopathy, or HIBM. It's a progressive muscle wasting disease that affects all of my muscles from head to toe. HIBM is very rare. In the United States there are less than 200 people diagnosed. To date, there is no proved treatment or cure, and within 10 to 15 years of its onset, HIBM typically leads to quadriplegia, which is why I now use a wheelchair. When I was first diagnosed, everything changed. It was frightening news because I had no experience with chronic illness or disabilities. And I had no idea how the disease might progress. But what was most disheartening was to listen to other people advise me to limit my ambitions and dreams, and to change my expectations of what to expect from life. "You should quit your international career." "No one will marry you this way." "You would be selfish to have children." The fact that someone who wasn't me
corriendo, saltando y bailando. Me encanta bailar. Sin embargo, con veintitantos empecé a sufrir una serie de caídas inexplicables. Y unos años más tarde, me diagnosticaron una enfermedad genética recesiva llamada miositis por cuerpos de inclusión o MCI. Es una enfermedad degenerativa de los músculos que afecta a todos los músculos, desde la cabeza hasta los pies. La MCI es muy poco frecuente. En EE. UU. hay menos de 200 personas diagnosticadas. A día de hoy, no hay tratamiento efectivo o cura, y a los 10 o 15 años de su inicio, la MCI normalmente lleva a la tetraplejia, razón por la cual uso una silla de ruedas. Cuando me la diagnosticaron, todo cambió. Fue una noticia terrible porque no estaba familiarizada con enfermedades crónicas o minusvalías. No sabía cómo la enfermedad iba a continuar. Pero lo más desalentador era escuchar los consejos de otros que ponían límites a mis sueños y ambiciones, o me animaban a cambiar las expectativas de lo que esperaba de la vida. "Deberías dejar tu carrera internacional". "Nadie se casará contigo en tu estado". "Sería egoísta por tu parte tener hijos". El hecho de que alguien que no fuera yo
was putting limitations on my dreams and ambitions was preposterous. And unacceptable. So I ignored them. (Cheers and applause) I did get married. And I decided for myself not to have children. And I continued my career with the United Nations after my diagnosis, going to work for two years in Angola, a country recovering from 27 years of brutal civil war. However, it would be another five years until I officially declared my diagnosis to my employer. Because I was afraid that they would question my capacity to manage and I'd lose my job. I was working in countries where polio had been common, so when I overheard someone say that they thought I might have survived polio, I thought my secret was safe. No one asked why I was limping. So I didn't say anything. It took me over a decade to internalize the severity of HIBM, even as basic tasks and functions became increasingly difficult. Yet, I continued to pursue my dream of working all over the world, and was even appointed as a disability focal point for UNICEF in Haiti, where I served for two years after the devastating 2010 earthquake.
pusiera límites a mis sueños y aspiraciones era ridículo e inaceptable. Así que los ignoré. (Aclamaciones) (Aplausos) Me casé. Decidí por mí misma no tener hijos. Continué mi carrera en Naciones Unidas tras mi diagnóstico yendo a trabajar durante dos años a Angola, un país que empezaba a recuperarse tras 27 años de guerra civil. Aunque no fue hasta cinco años más tarde que anuncié mi enfermedad a mi jefe. Tenía miedo de que pusieran en duda mi capacidad de gestión y por ello, perder mi trabajo. Trabajaba en países donde la polio era habitual así que, cuando oía a alguien decir que pensaban que había sobrevivido a la polio, pensaba que mi secreto estaba a salvo. Nadie me preguntó por qué cojeaba. Así que no dí explicaciones. Tardé diez años en asimilar la gravedad de la MCI. Hasta las tareas y trabajos más sencillos eran cada vez más complicados. Aún así, continué con mi sueño de trabajar alrededor del mundo, y me asignaron un puesto de ayuda a minusválidos para UNICEF en Haití donde estuve dos años tras el devastador terremoto del 2010.
And then my work brought me to the United States. And even as the disease progressed significantly and I needed leg braces and a walker to get around, I still longed for adventure. And this time, I started dreaming of a grand outdoor adventure. And what's more grand than the Grand Canyon? Did you know that for every five million people who visit the Rim only one percent go down to the canyon's base? I wanted to be a part of that one percent. The only thing is -- (Applause) The only thing is that the Grand Canyon isn't exactly accessible. I was going to need some assistance to get down the 5,000-foot descent of vertical loose terrain. Now, when I face obstacles, fear doesn't necessarily immediately set in because I assume that one way or another, I'll figure it out. And in this case, my thought was, well, if I can't walk down, I could learn to ride a horse. So that's what I did. And with that fateful decision began a four-year commitment, tossing back and forth between fear and courage to undertake a 12-day expedition. Four days on horseback to cross Grand Canyon rim to rim, and eight days rafting 150 miles of the Colorado River, all with a film crew in tow. Spoiler alert -- we made it. But not without showing me how my deepest fear can somehow manifest a mirror response of equal courage. On April 13, 2018,
Después mi trabajo me trajo a EE. UU. Y, aunque mi enfermedad progresó considerablemente y necesitaba aparatos ortopédicos y andador para desplazarme, ansiaba tener aventuras. Esta vez empecé a soñar con una gran aventura al aire libre. Y, ¿qué es más grande que el Gran Cañón? ¿Sabían que de cada cinco millones de personas que visitan el Rim tan solo el 1 % baja hasta la base del cañón? Quería formar parte de ese 1 %. Lo único... (Aplausos) Lo único es que el Gran Cañón no es precisamente accesible. Iba a necesitar algo de ayuda para bajar los 1500 metros de descenso por terreno vertical irregular. Eso sí, cuando me enfrento a los obstáculos, el miedo no siempre aparece de inmediato porque doy por sentado que, de una u otra manera, lo superaré. Así que pensé: si no puedo bajar andando, aprenderé a montar a caballo. Y es lo que hice. Y con dicha decisión tomada en firme, empezó un compromiso de cuatro años en el que alternaba miedo y valor para emprender un viaje de 12 días. Cuatro días a caballo para ir de una punta del Gran Cañón a la otra, y ocho días de rafting para recorrer los 240 km del Río Colorado, todo ello junto a un equipo de rodaje. Alerta de spoiler: lo conseguimos. Pero no sin enseñarme cómo mis miedos más profundos podían crear una respuesta reflejo de un grado de valentía equivalente. El 13 de abril del 2018,
sitting eight feet above the ground, riding a mustang horse named Sheriff,
sentada a dos metros y medio sobre un caballo Mustang llamado Sheriff,
my first impression of Grand Canyon was one of shock and terror. Who knew I had a fear of heights. (Laughter) But there was no giving up now. I mustered up every ounce of courage inside me to not let my fear get the best of me. Embarking on the South Rim, all I could do to keep myself composed was to breathe deeply, stare up into the clouds and focus on my team's voices. But then, in the first hour, disaster struck. Unable to hold myself upright in the saddle, going down an oversized step, I flung forward and smacked my face on the back of the horse's head. There was panic, my head hurt fiercely, but the path was too narrow for us to dismount.
mi primera impresión del Gran Cañón fue de conmoción y de miedo. Quién podía imaginar que tenía miedo a las alturas. (Risas) Pero ahora no podía abandonar. Reuní hasta la última pizca de valor que había en mí para evitar que el miedo se apoderara de lo mejor de mí misma. Embarcados en el South Rim, lo único que podía hacer para mantenerme tranquila era respirar profundamente, mirar las nubes y concentrarme en las voces de mi equipo. Pero entonces, durante la primera hora, ocurrió el desastre. Incapaz de mantenerme erguida en la silla, cuando descendíamos un escalón enorme, me deslicé y me golpeé la cara contra la cabeza del caballo. Todo el mundo se asustó, me dolía intensamente la cabeza, pero el camino era demasiado estrecho para poder bajarme.
Only at the halfway point at 2,300 feet, at least another two hours down, could we stop and remove my helmet and see the egg-sized bump protruding from my forehead. For all of that planning and gear, how is it that we didn't even have an ice pack? (Laughter) Luckily for all of us, the swelling came outwards, and would drain into my face as two fantastic black eyes which is an amazing way to look in a documentary film. (Laughter) (Applause and cheers) This was not an easy, peaceful journey, and yet, that was exactly the point. Even though I was afraid to get back into the saddle, I got back in. The descent alone to the canyon floor took a total of 10 hours and that was just day one of four riding. Next came the mighty rapids. The Colorado River in the Grand Canyon has some of the highest white water in the country. And just to be prepared in case we should capsize, we'd practice having me swim through a smaller rapid. And it's safe to say it wasn't glamorous. (Laughter) I took my breath in the wrong part of the wave, choked on river water and was unable to steer myself. Yes, it was scary, but it was also fantastic. Waterfalls, slick canyons
No fue hasta la mitad del recorrido, a unos 700 metros, al menos dos horas después, que pudimos parar, quitarme el casco y ver el chichón del tamaño de un huevo que sobresalía en mi frente. Con tanta planificación y materiales, ¿cómo es posible que no lleváramos una bolsa con hielo? (Risas) Por suerte para todos, la inflamación dio la cara, y se manifestó en forma de dos maravillosos ojos morados que es lo más apropiado para salir en un documental. (Risas) (Aplausos) (Aclamaciones) No fue un viaje fácil ni tranquilo aunque no fuera el objetivo. Aunque me daba miedo volver a montarme, lo hice. Solo para descender a la base del cañón tardamos 10 horas y era el primer día de cuatro a caballo. Luego fue el turno de los potentes rápidos. El Río Colorado en el Gran Cañón ofrece algunos de los rápidos más fuertes del país. Para prepararnos en caso de vuelco hicimos pruebas en tramos más fáciles. Les puedo asegurar que no fue demasiado elegante. (Risas) Tomaba aire cuando no debía, me atragantaba con el agua y era incapaz de estabilizarme. Sí, fue aterrador pero también fantástico. Cascadas, cañones resbaladizos
and a couple billion years of bedrock that seemed to change color throughout the day. The Grand Canyon is true wilderness and worthy of all of its accolades. (Applause) The expedition, all that planning and the trip itself, showed me a level of fear I had never experienced before. But more importantly, it showed me how boldly courageous I can be. My Grand Canyon journey was not easy. This was not a vision of an Amazonian woman effortlessly making her way through epic scenery. This was me crying, exhausted and beat up with two black eyes. It was scary, it was stressful, it was exhilarating.
y rocas sólidas de 2000 millones de años parecían cambiar de color conforme pasaba el día. El Gran Cañón es naturaleza silvestre digna de todos los elogios. (Aplausos) La expedición, tanto la planificación como el viaje en sí mismo, me mostró un grado de miedo que nunca antes había sentido. Pero, lo más importante, me mostró lo valiente que puedo llegar a ser. Mi viaje al Gran Cañón no fue fácil. No fue como si una amazonas recorriera sin esfuerzo alguno su camino con un escenario épico de fondo. Sino, yo llorando, agotada y con los ojos morados. Fue aterrador, estresante, excitante.
Now that the trip is over, it's easy to be blasé about what we achieved. I know I want to raft the river again. This time, all 277 miles of it. (Applause) But I also know that I would never do the horseback-riding part again. (Laughter) It's just too dangerous. And that's my real point. I'm not just here to show you my film footage. I'm here to remind us all that life is really just a lesson in finding the balance between fear and courage. And understanding what is and what isn't a good idea. (Laughter) Life is already scary, so for our dreams to come true, we need to be brave. In facing my fears and finding the courage to push through them, I swear my life has been extraordinary. So live big and try to let your courage outweigh your fear. You never know where it might take you. Thank you. (Applause and cheers)
Con el viaje ya acabado, es fácil no darle importancia a lo que conseguimos. Sé que quiero volver a hacer el rafting. Esta vez, los 445 kilómetros. (Aplausos) Pero también sé que nunca más haré la parte de montar a caballo. (Risas) Es demasiado peligroso. Y este es mi objetivo. No estoy aquí solo para enseñarles mi película. Estoy aquí para recordarles que la vida nos enseña a encontrar el equilibrio entre el miedo y el valor. Y a entender lo que es y lo que no es una buena idea. (Risas) La vida es de por sí aterradora, por lo que para que nuestros sueños se cumplan, necesitamos ser valientes. El enfrentarme a mis miedos y encontrar el valor para superarlos, ha hecho que mi vida sea extraordinaria. Así que, vivan a lo grande e intenten que su valor tenga más peso que su miedo. Nunca se sabe hasta dónde pueden llegar. Gracias. (Aplausos) (Aclamaciones)